STEPHEN J. O'CONNOR

8750 52nd Avenue East, Bradenton Florida 34211 • (925) 262-3633 • stitmoc@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Business Executive / Information Technology Executive who advances company mission through transformational innovation and global, cross-cultural leadership. Accomplished executive who develops and drives large-scale, IT innovation, while enhancing corporate profitability. Seasoned expert in board collaboration, rigorous operations, business transformation, digital transformation, continuous improvement, turn-around programs, and financial management. Individual who enjoys work while enjoying family, reading, sports, and helping others achieve personal goals and dreams.

SELECTED ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Information Technology Leadership As Chief Information Officer for \$4.1B P&C insurance enterprise, transformed legacy IT culture and IT environment into model of operational excellence, continuous improvement, and continuous delivery of business value. Significantly improved the customer experience both insurance purchasers and service agents. Transformed IT Strategy, Cyber Security environment and Digital innovation framework.
- **General Management,** Software Products -- Leading IT Business Management division at BMC Software, drove year on year sales growth of 402%. Improved business sales strategy, integration, revenue development, marketing, engineering, quality assurance, professional services, and customer support.
- Co-Founder, Information Technology Business Management Software firm As co-founder and GM, created ITM Software, driving international sales, product management, marketing execution, professional services departments, and customer support. Drove a substantial sales pipeline, successfully closing dozens of ITM Software product and services sales.
- Author <u>Building Professional Services: the Sirens' Song</u> Co-authored comprehensive guide to creating professional services organizations, managing them to maturity, and delivering both quality services and superior margins. This text introduces a complete, practical framework for delivering the full spectrum of professional services.
- Enterprise leader of global Information Technology platforms While Chief Information Officer at Silicon Graphics, developed and implemented the global technology strategy and operational framework. Managed and optimized annual operating budget of 235 Million Dollars with a direct staff of 725. Drove 20% reduction in sustaining expense.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

CSAA Insurance Group (AAA Company), Walnut Creek, CA

4.1B Property and Casualty Insurance firm, serving all regions of the United States

2011 to 2018

Vice President and Chief Information Officer

- Created, developed and implemented Information Technology strategy for CSAA Insurance Group, transforming legacy technologies, infrastructures and application suites into an innovation model that supports growth to \$4.1B+.
- Updated and optimized applications services into a best-in-class, agile development team, sustained by enterprise-wide ITIL practices and operational excellence.
- Reduced cost of IT, accelerated product and service delivery, while increasing customer satisfaction.
- Optimized diverse sourcing model with quantified, risk-based analysis, balancing in-house expertise, external trusted providers, owned infrastructure, and cloud-hosted technology.
- Institutionalized fact-based metrics accountability, and financial excellence:
 - Optimized and managed operating budget of \$215M (2018), project portfolio budget of \$50M, and a transformation budget of \$600M (2011 through 2017).
 - O Drove marked business efficiency (32% to 27% expense ratio).
 - o Dramatically reduced cost of Information Technology from 11% to 5% as percent of net revenue.
 - o Protected and grew the business core while developing and implementing advanced company-wide innovation.
- Created and launched Corporate Digital Services department and execution model, transforming customer experiences for over 1M clients, increasing profitability of corporate product suite, and driving innovation mindset.
- Transformed Cyber Security strategy, via a risk analysis paradigm, and instituting operational excellence across Digital Identity management, Cyber Awareness, Security Engineering, Strategy and Compliance, and Security Incident management. Collaborated with Corporate Privacy, Compliance and Legal.

BMC Software, Inc., San Jose, CA

2008 - 2011

1B Business Management Software firm, with international footprint and broad global sales

General Manager and Vice President

- Leader of IT Business Management software suite of products and cross-functional sales and operations team.
- Drove fastest initial two-year growth rate of any previous BMC acquisition 402% year over year.
- Achieved growth across all areas, including license sales, maintenance, and professional services.
- Achieved 95% renewal rate of existing customers and drove maintenance agreement expansion.
- Captured new business for ITBM that was leveraged across other infrastructure software sold by the firm.
- Developed integration strategy with other BMC Software Business units, to cross-sell software and services via synchronized sales processes and integrated software tools.
- Directly managed marketing, sales, product management, engineering, quality assurance, professional services, and customer support functions.
- Successfully integrated ITM Software into BMC Software with less than 5% attrition, exceeding all financial goals established by BMC Board of Directors for the acquisition.

ITM Software, Inc. Mountain View, California

2001 - 2008

Business Management Software company, creating executive insight through analytics

Co-Founder and General Manager

- Personally envisioned, designed and developed business intelligence automation concept for Information Technology leaders, culminating in a comprehensive business management product suite
- Created value proposition that was *chronicled by Forester Research and Gartner* -- advancing CIO management and executive staff performance via analytical, process-based system of record for IT value management.
- Oversaw and led product design, development, quality assurance, product release, customer deployments and customer value realization.
- Sold and deployed platform to 40 customers, worldwide.
- Led and secured over \$50M in venture capital funding.
- Led successful exit with sale of product and company to BMC Software in 2008.

Silicon Graphics, Inc. Mountain View, California

1995 - 2001

Vice President – Global Professional Services

(2000-2001)

- Drove \$120-million in revenue while leading 450-person global staff.
- Led and optimized the business strategy, architecture, and operating plan across broad range of corporate products and services.
- Drove innovation for clients, by leading architecture, development, implementation, and support of custom computing solutions, directed at technical and creative customer base.
- Derived 100% revenue growth from 1999 to 2000 (\$60M to \$120M). Most significant accomplishments included business growth and *transforming the business from operating loss to profitability*.

Chief Information Officer and Vice President Information Technology

(1997 - 2000)

- Led enterprise-wide, global, information technology strategy, architecture, and execution.
- Optimized operating budget of \$235M, and direct staff of 725.
- Successfully deployed global ERP System and customer support application suite (Clarify), electronic commerce solution, Y2 compliance, solid sustaining operations.
- Drove a reduction in Information technology budget of 20% during three-year period.

Director - Networks, Application Development & Support, and End User Computing Services

(1995 - 1997)

Other IT leadership positions at Sun Microsystems, Cullinet Software and Raytheon in Application Services, Customer Service, Development and Engineering, 1985 – 1997.

EDUCATION

Juris Doctorate, Law, Suffolk University, School of Law, Boston, MA

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science; School of Management, Boston College, Chestnut Hill, MA

Diploma, College Preparation, Xaverian Brothers High School, Westwood, MA